Can you give us some reasons men quit
testosterone replacement therapy?
>> Some reasons uh why someone may quit?
>> Yeah.
>> So, I am of a belief that if you begin
testosterone replacement for the correct
reasons, you should stay on it forever.
Now, my office will not start someone on
testosterone for any reason outside of
what we deem to be a medical deficiency.
Medical deficiencies are not necessarily
defined by clinical numbers in and of
themselves as a guideline, but that is
certainly a part of it. They are also
defined by lifestyle variables, age, uh
symptoms, etc. So if we determine you
are deficient or that the potential
risks which we mitigate quite well are
minimal compared to the potential reward
of going on therapy, we will initiate
therapy and generally that will be a
lifelong or presumably hopefully a
lifelong venture. We don't feel that
there is a reason to ever come off
testosterone replacement when it's
managed correctly or when you get on for
the right reasons. And therefore I see
no medical reason for someone to
discontinue treatment unless
there are environmental factors or
selfdestructive
factors. So for example, I will not
treat smokers. I will not treat people
who are severely or morbidly obese. Uh I
will make sure that all of that is
addressed prior to initiating therapy.
And that is because the risk associated
of liability to us is greater with those
individuals. With that said, that is
just my philosophy on on treatment. With
that said, there are people who often
choose to come off for various reasons.
It could be a personal decision which I
don't necessarily have to agree with but
I have to respect from a patient's
perspective or it may be another
provider who disagrees with the
treatment and talks the patient into
coming off which again I don't have to
agree with but often times I have to
sort of mitigate
uh why people come off people come off
because they feel that they're not
feeling a tangible benefit to treatment
which often times I try to tell patients
there's many intangible benefits that
you may not necessarily feel it doesn't
mean the treatment is not working for
you. It just means that if your symptoms
are unresolved by treatment perhaps
those specific symptoms are secondary to
other causes which you should explore.
Uh sometimes people have a provider who
doesn't feel that they should be on
testosterone whether it be a urologist,
endocrinologist, cardiologist or primary
care provider and they talk them into
coming off treatment. Again, I don't
necessarily agree with it, but those are
the most common reasons that I see why
men discontinue treatment. Um like I
said, I don't agree with them, but uh
those are probably the most common.
>> Sure. Um yeah and and the common reasons
like high hematocrit or um a PSA that is
too high all those things
>> right that's usually why another
provider will tell them to come off
again we don't necessarily agree with
that philosophy we believe that the
testosterone in of itself does not cause
harm in those scenarios but if those
scenarios exist they should be explored
for the main culprit or the the reason
why they exist and that should be
rectified
rather than just pulling someone off
therapy and allowing them to suffer and
often times they just spiral into worse
health overall. So, um but yeah, a lot
of people believe that testosterone is
the evil force behind some of these
unwanted uh outcomes and it's it's a
shame.